this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant detailed
discussions about software engineering
topics at least once a month
thanks to our audience and the partners
listed on our website for supporting the
podcast
[Music]
all right so my name is Martina father
and the manager of scientific outreach
at the University of Waterloo and for
the Institute for quantum computing okay
so this answers my question whether I
should pronounce your name English or
French French if possible but I got used
to both of them so it's fine okay how
would I do it in English laughs first
yeah and people say Martin LaForest okay
okay so um what's your group about what
you're doing there which Institute oh
are you working for so I'm working for
the Institute for quantum computing we
are a very large Institute part of the
University of Waterloo in Canada so what
we do here is we have about a hundred
researcher and it's we have 17 faculty
members right now about 25 to 28
postdocs and 85 undergraduate and
graduate students and what we do here is
we're trying to harness a quantum world
and understand how we can use it to
perform quantum information processing
and one of the particularity of our
Institute is that we're trying to attack
the problem from pretty much all the
angle possible so either from the
implementation side with the physicists
and the engineers that works in the lab
or works under the theory of
implementation but also we have a lot of
people about half or a researcher
working on the computing side or the
communication side the very theory very
abstract way of understanding really
what quantum resource can give us or how
you can use quantum resource to do
information processing so we're really
trying to tackle the problem from every
angle and trying to understand really
and what we can do with it and trying
also to make it happen
so so this episode is primarily about
quantum computing but you already
mentioned quantum information processing
and there are other terms like quantum
communication and stuff can you maybe
delineate those terms and explain what
the differences are and what kind of
computing specifically is yes absolutely
so quantum computing is really the the
science of using the quantum world the
quantum resource to do as it says
computing trying to make some computing
tasks solving some
mathematical problem or other related
problem that a classical computer might
not be able to do or might take a long
time to do but this is one part of a
larger field we call either quantum
information processing or quantum
information technology and this anglo
essentially anything that is related to
information processing using quantum
resource it can be related to for
example quantum cryptography quantum
communication it can also go to quantum
sensing quantum Allen actuators but
quantum computing is one subset of all
those possibilities that we can do with
the quantum world ok so I guess before
we go into the somewhat of the details
what kind of high school physics do
listeners have to know I mean we all
probably know something about this
quantum world which is quote strange
where you know probabilities rule and
where nothing is like it seems yeah so
can you maybe give us a little bit of a
quick you know recap of the high school
physics we need so in the high school a
few people go in the core of what
quantum mechanic is okay that's a
university physics yeah one of the
little experiment that a lot of people
see in a high school or at least in
undergraduate studies is the young
double slit experiment which essentially
demonstrates what quantum mechanics
really is so if people recall the young
double slit experiment is shining a
laser to two very tiny slit and what we
expect is if we shine the light through
one slit you get one blurb on the screen
on the other side of the slit shine the
light to the outer slit you also have
one blur right so what you would expect
normally is if you shine the light
through two double slit you would get to
burn but that's not what you get at all
you get an interference pattern with
some bright spot and dark spot and
bright spot and dark spot mm-hmm
essentially the way normally in high
school you explain that is it shows the
the wave property of light exactly yeah
if you see light as a wave then it will
interfere then you can explain that the
same way as for example of water wave
would do the exact same thing going
through two slit mm-hmm well where it
becomes particular is that you can also
do that with just single photon at the
time so one particle of light where you
cannot have a smaller amount of light
possible so you
on divisible yeah and if you consider
that this way you will still also see a
pattern at the end on the screen and the
only way you can explain that pattern is
if you model the whole thing as the
photon going through the two slit at the
same time so you have one photon you can
pass through the two slit and it
essentially interfere with itself okay
and that shows very well one of the
remarkable property of quantum mechanics
that we call quantum superposition which
essentially says that a quantum particle
or quantum system can be in more than
one state at the same time so it's just
superposition of state and in this case
with the double slit is the
superposition of going through the loop
right slit and the left slit at the same
time I guess there is not much of a
point of trying to like really
understand this it's just the way it is
right essentially yes quantum mechanics
is we can say the ultimate laws of how
nature works so when you go down to the
building blocks of nature we're talking
like molecules electrons protons
neutrons at this point the laws of
classical mechanics are essentially you
know the Newton laws or the laws of
electromagnetism from the Maxwell's
equation for example they cannot explain
how molecules behave or how electron
behave for example and that's where
quantum mechanics come in essentially
it's a rather theory that really explain
what happened when you go to the very
small mm-hmm technically it would also
explain that we the word like awkward or
microscopic word also work but it's just
those quantum if they are so small yeah
that in our everyday life we don't
really precede them it's a little bit
like a relativity every ball that falls
from a tree has relativistic effects but
they're so small you can just as well
use Newton it's good enough exactly so
the Newton's equation or an extremely
precise approximation for a word yeah
but when you go to a little deeper what
nature is it doesn't hold anymore right
so which physical properties are
quantified I seem to remember spin right
yeah spin is an example of a quantum
property that we don't really see on
everyday life but if you look at this
spin is essentially just like a tiny
spinning magnet it has a
magnetic dipole moment but the only
difference is that when you put it in a
magnetic field as long as you don't look
at it as long as you don't measure it it
can point along the magnetic field
against a magnetic field or you can
point in any direction it can be in a
superposition of pointing along or
against once you look at it unlike a
classical dipolar moment you will only
measure it as either pointing along or
pointing against mm-hmm so here I'm
talking about a spin 1/2 there's all
other type of spins than once then 3 1/2
and so on but a spin 1/2 for example
where when you measure it will always
either point along the magnetic field or
against so there's only two discrete
state it can have ok other quantum
quantities or characteristics of atoms
that are interesting for working in
quantum computing or quantum or
exploiting quantum effects in general
you mentioned a lot of atoms and
molecules but that's not the only thing
that shows quantum effect right right if
you take for example one of the possible
system we investigate for quantum
computing is a superconducting qubit
that we call and this is actually a
fairly large systems about on the
micrometer size
it's a nano sized electrical circuit but
by adding in a few of you element of
superconducting material that we call
Josephson Junction then you can also
start seeing some quantum effect and one
example the one we call the flux qubit
you can have the current in your circuit
either going around the loop clockwise
or around the loop counterclockwise or
you can also be in a superposition of
both clockwise and anti-clockwise ok so
that's another property for example we
can use so you mentioned spin spin is
somewhat a natural candidate for doing
quantum computing because it really has
two discrete state mm-hmm but at the end
of the day if you take any quantum
system that has a certain property that
has two discrete level that can be
accessed in a quantum mechanical way
this is potentially a candidate for a
qubit as I mentioned superconducting you
can think of an ion for example where it
can be in the ground state or in an
excited state that could be or to stay
for your qubit a photon is a great
example you can use a photon in many
different ways to do a qubit you can use
polarization a photon can be polarized
vertically can be polarized horizontally
but can also be polarized at any other
angle okay that can seen as a
superposition of horizontal and vertical
yeah or the photon you can also use you
can use what we call the spatial
distribution of the photon where we can
take a photon through a beam splitter
you can go right or left so we can call
the right your zero for a qubit or the
left your one for the qubit and that you
can do that in the quantum way which
means that you can be in both the left
and right fibre okay or you can use that
again with the photon you can use a
frequency you have a center frequency
you can then your qubit can be either
the frequencies a little higher or a
little lower use that as your qubit so
there are many different voices maybe
out there more than a dozen proposal of
different systems okay you bet mm-hmm
and of course the qubit is is the the
same thing as the bit in classical
computing is the quantum bit that is
basically the on/off or zero one state
although it can be in several states
which is the whole point of quantum
computing this is the whole point yeah
so at the end of the day we still work
with binary calculus with so zero and
one that's still your answer you're
gonna get at the end but by having a
quantum bit then you can have your zero
in one behaving quantum mechanically so
you can be in a superposition of 0 n one
okay and here we see but Eisley a lot of
0 and 1 and people might get confused of
when we start doing probabilistic
classical computing where you can have a
chance of being in 0 or a chance of
being in 1 where the probability is any
number between 0 and 1 right probability
can only be a positive number in quantum
mechanics that's where the the beauty
comes in we don't work with probability
but we work with probability and clits
you and those probability amplitude can
be any number on what we call the
complex circle so it can be a negative
number can be a positive number it can
be an imaginary number a complex number
okay so let's get back a step yes um if
if we assumed we would do classical we
would write classical programs with
quantum computing which we don't and
we'll get back to that but then we could
assume that a bit isn't just a simple 0
or 1 but rather
well in the end this is the role one but
but but while we compute it can be any
value at the same time yes it can be put
in any superposition you won
and in that superposition as I was
saying can take any value between any
complex number value yeah and then once
you measure then the the observation
effect kicks in and then it has to
decide what it wants to be kind of
exactly so once you measure you will
only get probabilistically a 0 or a 1
and then that relates back to to this
probability amplitude thing is that the
the probability of measuring assert that
either is 0 or the 1 will be equal to
the modulus square of this probability
amplitude so at the end of the day you
still measure the answer with a certain
probability yeah but where the whole
quantum mechanical things comes in is
because we can have negative or complex
probability amplitude then later on in
your computation it can lead to
interference so we can lead for example
to the probability of measuring one can
interfere with itself and cancel out so
that at the end you can only measure
zero so that's a bit of a simplistic way
of seeing this but that's a little bit
higher works by accessing the quantum
mechanical property of those cubed then
you can you have access to interference
so the reason why I'm kind of
emphasizing that is that I want to try
to get to the point where it becomes
clear that this is not the same as fuzzy
logic where you also have instead of
having zeros and ones you have a
continuum of basically real numbers
between zeros and bonding you somehow
calculate with not probabilities but
with with analog values if you will zero
to one non zero and one but this is
different because the system can be in
several states or maybe all states at
the same time which is not true for
fuzzy logic that's absolutely right I'm
not entirely familiar with that me
neither
but yeah at the end of the day the only
thing I can say is the main difference
between probabilistic classical
computing and quantum computing was that
we don't only have access to positive
number but we have access to all
possible number and that was brings all
the remarkable properties of quantum
computing ok
so I mean I'm a software developer so I
know how to write
deterministic well they're not always
deterministic but I hope they're
deterministic program and I know what to
do with that and how this works I mean
how can you do anything useful in an
environment where kind of everything
happens at the same time so what do you
do with quantum computing and then I
mean how do you tackle it how do you
actually make this do something useful I
mean this is a very hard question and
you know building quantum algorithm I
have to admit is not an easy science
it's extremely hard you need to develop
a very good intuition for quantum
mechanics for it but at the end of the
day to answer your question of how can
we get the right answer if everything is
probabilistic
is that we just need to be a little more
clever I'll give you a very very naive
picture which is not the whole story but
you can see it this way well let's say
we try to compute a certain problem
which writes find the the answer to a
certain problem okay so we know the
algorithm to verify that the answer is
true right so what we can do for example
we can use your quantum or quantum
system and put it an all possible answer
and then you use the quantum algorithm
to check if that answer is true so now
because your quantum system is an all
possible answer by applying that quantum
algorithm is going to verify each
possible answer and see if it's true and
what you can do is if it turns out to be
true the quantum algorithm can
essentially tag that little state so at
that point your quantum computer is
still in all the superposition of how
the answer but the one that gives you
the right answer will be tagged and then
you can add an extra layer of algorithm
to it so they're only the answer that
got tagged will have a probability of
being measured and all the other one
will just not be measure at all so
that's how you can transform a
probabilistic algorithm into a more
deterministic one so this is one way of
doing it and that we call amplitude
amplification so you amplify the
amplitude of measuring the right answer
this is not the only way there's also
other ways of doing it by computing more
using the phase of the of the states and
that's really when you start tackling
the quantum mechanic a lot because you
work with probability amplitude and I
say those amplitude
any complex number you can sort of
encode all your information in the phase
of the state and then again use a very
clever algorithm to and then to make all
the wrong answer interfere and not give
you a new probability of measuring and
then all the right answer to interfere
constructively so that they will be
measure at the end this and I I say
again this is a very naive way of saying
things and things are much more complex
in real life but that sort of give the
idea of how we can work right so if you
say we amplify the amplitude and we mark
something and things like that this is
all physical interactions this is not a
program in that sense that you write in
some particular quantum programming
language right this is all this is all
Hardware if you will well you know at
the end of the day right with you know
what a computer language is it's just a
shortcut to tell your computer what to
do yes right right at the end of the day
the computer what it does is it take the
bit and then flip downs and then make
them interact with another bit but when
you use a language like C or Python it's
just a quick shortcut that when you see
multiplying then it knows that it has to
do implement in the processor the
multiplication algorithm so in quantum
computing is essentially the same thing
well we're just not at the point of
having a high-level programming language
yet I mean some people do program some
sort of compiler or language but at the
end of the day is really a shortcut that
tells your electronics to do something
and that something is either you know
yeah flip a bit make that bit interact
with the other qubit and then that qubit
measure that 2 bit and according to the
measurement do something else so at the
end of the day is very hard where do you
still need to go control your pin there
but but you're right a minute sorry it's
yeah it's not that different from having
a transistor you know that does
something on a chip and then having
another transistor that does something
with the output from the first
transistor and stuff it's just that this
is also highly integrated these days
that you don't notice this and you
actually kind of have a program yeah
exactly so now it is so well integrated
we don't even think what's going on in
the processor but if you go back in the
early days of the computer know that's
what they were doing they were telling
the computer me back then it was a
vacuum tube so they were
they're representing each vacuum -
Ronnie you're gonna add a switch a
signal on that side or switch Arsenal on
the other side and then you know really
step by step so we're essentially there
right now in quantum computing we still
work on the alchemy sale on the machine
language yeah we directly tell the
Cubist's what to do and also staying in
the analogy you don't even know that
it's going to be transistors in the
sense that you are still experimenting
with different physical representations
of qubits yes as I was saying before
there's about a dozen probably more than
a dozen proposal all of them have some
very good point and most of them also
have some bad parts so we haven't found
the holy grail of the qubit yeah yeah so
that's why we're no different people
work on different different technologies
but you know some some people working
with photons some people working with
superconductors semiconductors ion trap
you name it so there's not one consensus
yet of what the quantum computer will
actually look like at the end of the day
right that's why we do research we're
we're still trying to either find the
Holy Grail or just use what we know now
and then prove it and and then at the
end trying to make it behave the way we
want because that's a problem with
quantum mechanics it is stubborn lean
classical it doesn't like to stay
quantum mechanical okay and by that what
I say is that this famous quantum
superposition I'm talking about yes it's
an extremely fragile state so once you
have a system in a quantum superposition
it or any quantum system tend to
interact with its environment it's very
similar as if the environment was
actually reading the state run by
reading the state then it brings it from
a quantum superposition into a classical
statistical mixture so you have from the
quantum to just a probabilistic bit and
most of the effort nowadays and pretty
much all the all the system is to be
that interaction with the environment
I'm called decoherence so we're trying
to better isolate our system from the
environment right but you cannot
completely isolate your system from the
environment because at the end of the
day you need to manipulate your system
coupled to it so it's a bit of a
catch-22 in some sense what you want to
do is you kind of want to insert the
problem and then you want it to be
completely isolated and then once
finished however you know this then you
want to put another probe to measure the
result kind of well this is a
measurement yes but to do the to
implement an algorithm or to just
control your system you need an external
system to control it I'll just take for
example we were talking about spin spin
as a fantastic candidate for a qubit
because it only has two level and
normally it's somewhat very well
isolated from the environment but if you
want to control them then you need to
use microwave or radio wave so you need
to couple an external system to your
isolated system to control it mm-hmm so
if an oocyte is isolated very well you
still need to annihilate it to control
it and that's one of the large challenge
how can you control it without
disturbing it too much or without making
it interact with things that you don't
have control over ie what we call the
environment so that's one of the main
challenge nowadays and then you
mentioned also at the end of the day you
want to measure your result that's also
a challenge in some some technologies
are very good at measuring some of them
are not very good so as I was saying you
know all technologies have their good
point and that they have the bad their
bad point yeah is it expected that there
will be one common standardized
representation of a qubit like the
transistor in classical computing or do
you think I mean of course we don't know
but what's the community opinion that
will there be different representations
for different tasks or kinds of problems
well one thing that people seems to go
toward is that we're most likely going
to be moving toward a hybrid quantum
computer and by that what I mean is you
might have a some sort of processor that
might work with either a spin or an ion
or you name it to do your computation
but then if you want to send your
information or your quantum information
or send your quantum answer somewhere
else you might have to couple it to what
we call the flying qubit so a qubit that
can actually transport that information
which you know at the end of they might
most likely be a photon yeah no I'm not
saying that would 100% certainty but the
photons are great because they travel at
the speed of light because they are
light and the they tend to interact very
little that with their environment so
once you've been able to put your
quantum information in the photon you
can send it down
fiber or free space at the speed of
light without using too much of your
quantumness in your information yeah but
but this is you know this is one way at
the end of the day to answer more
clearly your question I don't think
there's a consensus yet okay as if there
was a consensus then everybody will be
researching on the same system yeah
right so I mean everybody Billy research
in their own system believe it might be
the system or it should be the system
yeah another consensus that seems to be
arising more and more nowadays is we try
to use existing technologies and push
them to the quantum limits to do quantum
computation I'll just come back to the
example of superconducting qubit mm-hmm
super grant alien qubit is made with
capacitor with inductors with resistors
and with those Josephson junctions so
that's this extra little tool that we
add of superconductors but at the end of
the day everything is built on a chip
with existing current technology for
doing example eating natok rafi or
atomic layer deposition so we can use
all the technology being developed in
the name of classical computing by the
chip builder companies who became
extremely good yeah
doing very small-scale pattern on the
chip so we're trying to essentially
leverage that knowledge or that
expertise and then use that and then
push it to the quantum limit mam
superconductor was one example or you
can think also of building quantum dots
on on semiconductors right the entire
computer industry became really aware
how to work with semiconductors so here
we're trying to use it and then push it
to the quantum limit so let's take a
look at how a quantum computer today
looks I assume these are still rather
big machines I've seen photographs you
know with lasers and colorful lights and
big metal thingies so can you explain I
mean obviously as you say there are
several but can you pick an example of
like the physical components that go
into such a machine how it looks and how
it works
sure maybe the example I can take is
nuclear magnetic resonance
okay in nuclear magnetic resonance we
use the spin of the nuclei in an
ensample of molecule to do quantum
computation so we know nowadays that we
will never be able to build a quantum
computer with nuclear magnetic resonance
because
first of all we don't control single
molecules but an in symbol of molecules
and that leads to a whole other set of
problems so at the end of the day the
scalability of that system is Joe
paradise because it has very little
polarization but we're getting a little
technical okay to explain how this look
in the lamb is so first of all to have
the spin in order to separate the two
state and so in order to have a
separation between this what we call a
spin up or spin down right a little spin
pointing along a magnetic field or I
guess magnetic field well you need a
magnetic field and for nuclear magnetic
resonance you need very large magnetic
field or order of you know one to ten 20
Tesla so you have a very big Ken that
looks like a beer keg
can be all the way up to a couple meters
in diameter maybe even bigger to a
couple meters 3 meters high so that can
be very large but this is really just to
have a really big superconducting magnet
for example one we have here is we have
this fifteen point three Tesla magnet
which is two hundred thousand times
bigger than the magnetic field of the
earth so you don't want to have your
credit card on you so this is really
just to put your n symbol of molecule in
the middle of the magnet and that's to
provide that energy separation between
being pointing a long minute fill or
against okay it will take less energy to
point along and more energy to point
against because at the end of the day
nature is lazy always likes to be in the
low energy state the spin will naturally
point along the magnetic field so that
would be to initialize your computer for
example but now you want to make your
qubit perform operation so you need to
control them you need to go from a spin
up to a superposition of spin up and
down and that for doing this we use
radio wave so that's where the whole
resonance come in for nuclear magnetic
resonance and essentially the idea of
this the way it works is rather simple
you can think about it as when you were
in grade school and the merry-go-round
so you were turning around the
merry-go-round and then this is what a
spin does when you put it in a magnetic
field in a superposition so if you put a
spin in a superposition a magnetic field
it precess around the manatee
feel that you know quite high-value they
make depending on the size of the magnet
they can go several hundred million turn
a second okay working with you know
hundreds of megahertz now if you want to
make them flip or make them spin what we
use is we use a rotating magnetic field
so I'm going back to my merry-go-round
example let's say you're on the
merry-go-round and you're spinning
around and you're trying to talk to your
friend on the ground then it would be
very hard to talk because you can really
only talk when the spinning guy arrived
close right but then goes away you
cannot talk anymore because you can hear
each other but if your friends start
running around at the same frequency as
the merry-go-round can as far as you're
concerned your friend is just right
beside you and never move so we can have
a conversation you know your friend will
be out of breath but you can still talk
so that's essentially what we do here is
by sending a magnetic field pointing in
a certain direction but also rotating at
the same frequency as the spin as far as
the spin is concerned it sees a certain
magnetic field in the constant direction
and start rotating around it and that's
how the whole radio wave comes in
because a radio wave is essentially a
rotating magnetic field well when you
connect a radio wave to an inductor then
it creates a oscillating magnetic field
and then that approximately very well to
a rotating magnetic field so this way by
having this oscillating magnetic field
at the same frequency as your procession
of your spin then you can start making
them rotate about any angle you want so
that is for creating what we call a
single qubit operation so you can
control single spin this way so
basically you can set a qubit to a
certain value if you will well to a
certain superposition of values yes yes
okay and here I mentioned NMR but if you
work with spin in a quantum dot is the
exact same principle and then we became
so good in NMR at controlling this eye
we can create the exact superposition we
want with a precision of 99.999 five
percent okay so NMR in term of control
is it's very good so as I was saying we
know that NMR is sort of joke or dies in
terms of scalability yeah it's a
fantastic testbed because it is a
working prototype of a quantum computer
so we can develop techniques in this
system that can later on be applied to
different system that use the same sort
of dynamics or also you spin okay so but
at this point we just put values in
right there hasn't been any calculation
or operation yet well this thing of
rotating the spin is an operation
example if you do a rotation of 180
degrees then you took your spin up into
a spin down so you essentially did a not
gate okay a 0 into a1 or if you just do
a 90-degree rotation then you turn your
0 into a superposition an equal
superposition of 0 and 1 and this is an
operation that is extremely critical in
cloning computing that we call the
oedema operation which create a
superposition of 0 and 1 out of a
classical state of 0 or 1 ok but so far
I only mentioned the radio wave for
controlling a single qubit but if we
have a molecule with several nuclei
several different nuclei now let's say
we have three different nuclei that we
can control so using radio wave right
now it only gives us three one qubit
processor you need to make them interact
with each other because you know where
you can just control one qubit but if
you don't make it interact with another
qubit then you don't have a two qubit
system I just have two one qubits this
absolutely mm-hmm actually Nature has
been nice enough we're in the spin
example that the naturally interact with
each other so if you just let them go
they will interact and then they will
create what we call entanglement okay
that's another one of these quantum
effects right that's another one of this
quantum effect that we can come back a
little later it's a it's even more
remarkable than the superposition in my
belief okay but essentially we need
entanglement to really use all the power
of quantum computing and then in term of
spin system if it works yours naturally
is by letting them evolve they will
naturally interact with each other so we
need to time the amount of time they
will interact to make a certain
operation okay so at the end of the day
what I'm saying is that we need
extremely precise radio wave generator
and we need an extremely precise timing
and one of the very nice little trivia
about for example nuclear magnetic
resonance spectrometer is that the
technology used for the timing is the
exact same technology we use in GP
yes the same type of clock right so
shrooming precise clock and they come
for cheap because GPS is you know wall
spread now yeah well yeah so this is one
example of one system the type of
infrastructure that we use the big
magnetic field radio wave timing and but
that you know this is just a very simple
way of seeing it if you see the big
machine there's a lot more electronics
evolving yeah and and to it so we use
the radio waves to put stuff in how do
we get stuff out how do we find out the
resulting superposition so this is
highly highly dependent on your system
in NMR for example to read out as I was
saying because we have a spin a spin is
the it looks like a tiny magnet you know
when it's in a certain superposition it
will rotate around the magnetic field so
because it's a rotating magnetic field
it will create a rotating electric field
mm-hm
that's one of the laws of
electromagnetism so you can think of
putting your system in the inductor or
like a coil
sorry no oil and then because their spin
turn around it will create a changing
magnetic field which in turn would
create a changing current in your
electrical circuit and then you can plug
that in an oscilloscope and then read ok
the frequency at which your spin rotates
and from that you can deduce the state
of all the other spin in your in your
module ok that's one example so
basically the way a quantum computer
works is as follows you have this
physical / mechanical equipment you
start up the system you use your input
facility in this case the radiation to
put your quantum thingies whatever you
use into a specific state or
superposition of states then we have
them interact you wait for a little
while because the time you give them for
the interaction determines how they
interact and then you measure the
resulting superpositions / spins in this
case yes this is a maybe a little too
simplistic at the end of the day a
quantum computer will work essentially
just like a regular computer so you need
to find a way to initialize your system
so for example when you start up your
computer you know all your system is
booted up you know exactly what state it
is right and then you want to do a
certain task
you have in that governor and an
algorithm is always broken up in terms
of smaller operation you know I apply
this I prefer operations the first qubit
this type of operation the third qubit
and then make the third and fourth qubit
interact and then so it's a series of
operation so this is the quantum
algorithm when you get into the physical
process then you need to translate all
those operation into physical operation
to relate to what I was talking like for
example if you have a single qubit
operation then it would be some radio
wave and then if you have two qubit
operation so in an interaction between
qubit one in qubits for then you will
have you will let your system evolve for
a certain time and then you will have
other single qubit operation and then
another two qubit or three qubit
operation so it's always a series of
different operation that we do
physically in the lamp so there's always
a need for translating the actual
algorithm that they give you step by
step what to do and do a physical action
of what we're gonna do like when we turn
off the radio wave generator and when we
let the system evolve freely and and so
on right but what we're explaining here
is what we call the circuit model it's
very based just like the classical
computing where you have certain bit and
then you do certain operations in you
know linearly or in parallel and so on
but that's only one type of model for
computing there's other proposal over
there one of them that it's becoming
more and more study this what we call
the measurement based quantum computer
and that one this way work is you start
with your system in a special state that
we call a cluster steam and then the way
you do computing is just by measuring
different qubits in different way and
depending on the answer then you change
the type of measurement you do later on
and that's how you create your
computation okay not by actively
controlling your Kuban but by actively
measuring them
that's another model not a bottle out
there also it's called the adiabatic
quantum computer which is I'm personally
not necessarily an expert in it but the
way it works is essentially your
algorithm is translated into a certain
dynamics of your system and by slowly
changing the dynamic of your system
toward what you
your quantum system will always remain
in the state of low energy and that
state at the end of the day gives you
the answer that's another type so
there's there's only one way of doing
computing with this different proposal
out there depending on the system so
some system are more suitable for a
measurement based some system are more
suitable for the circuit base order
system or more suitable for adiabatic so
at the end of the day quantum computing
there's many possible ways many
different system and then you know
there's research being done in all of
those because still early days it's
still the early days and we still don't
know which one's gonna win the race
right
you mentioned entanglement and as
something you wanted to come back to
because it's fascinating what's
entangled yes probably the most
counterintuitive property of that's good
because we didn't have any
counterintuitive stuff yet so great that
we have something counterintuitive so go
I counter intuitive so let's go even
more counter intuitive so the whole
superposition a quantum superposition
was when one quantum system can be in
multiple state at the same time now I'll
take two quantum system and then you can
put them in superposition also but you
can put them in such a superposition
that your two qubits or your two quantum
system are extremely correlated more
correlated that you can ever explain it
using just classical physics or
classical correlation and one of a
particular example I can say let's go in
a little bit of details but it's it
should not be too hard okay that's like
two photons okay so as I was saying you
can use as a qubit you can use the
polarization of the photon so you can
call your zero a photon having a
vertical polarization right and you can
call your one horizontal so now if you
look at a photon with the polarization
at 45 degrees then this is a
superposition of horizontal and vertical
yep just like you know basic Cartesian
coordinates right if you take two
entangled photon if we entangle them in
a certain in a special entangled State
what's gonna happen is if you measure
one qubit in the vertical polarization
or the horizontal if you measure it in
the vertical Horizonte
bayes's yeah once you measure one photon
you will know right away what was the
value of the other photon so if the
first photon gives you a horizontal you
know the other one was in the horizontal
it'd give you a vertical you know the
other one would be a vertical okay so
this is not surprising yet you can just
have two photon that are either
horizontal or either vertical that will
give you this correlation where the
whole quantum entanglement comes in and
that special entangle State is now if
you look in the other basis if you
measure your photon in the 45 or minus
45 degree if it's a classical state
measuring the state of one photon will
give you a half and half probability of
being either vertical or horizontal but
then measuring the other photon will
also give you a half or half probability
so they're not correlated anymore they
were correlated in one basis but not on
the other basis but that special quantum
state that entangles want of state that
we call also the EPR State for an stein
Podolsky and Rosen the people raised
that weirdness of quantum mechanic back
in the days if you take that state and
you measure in the 45-degree basis then
you will also know immediately what the
other one state is so essentially at the
end of the day what I'm saying is like
no matter and which angle will you
measure your photon it will always be
correlated with the other photon also
and this is something that classical
mechanics cannot explain and that is
something inherent to quantum mechanics
and that's what we call quantum
entanglement
so it's essentially just like you're too
much your to quantum system we're
behaving as if it was only one system
they're completely correlated they dance
together all the time no matter which
way you look at okay and it's currently
as far as I understand that unclear how
they exchange the information if you
will yes it's unclear some people take
the very pragmatic way essentially like
just people like me just say this is how
it happens it's and then we're happy
with it but there's also a whole lot of
people out there trying to understand
what is going on some people just say no
is it cannot just happen instantaneously
there's something missing there and that
brings the whole researcher on the the
foundation of quantum mechanics trying
to really
and what is going on which is at this
point it's it's more of a philosophical
question than a practical question so as
far as I'm personally concerned that's
how it content mechanics is described
that's how it works in the lamb I'm
happy with it and we just try to harness
it and then make some very neat stuff
with it actually this is a very good
Segway making some very neat stuff with
it we should talk a little bit about
what you do with this stuff so maybe to
again look at a last kind of theoretical
aspect in classical computing there is
the Turing machine yes this is basically
something that says what kind of
ingredients you need to be able to
calculate everything
it's very simplified yeah so and it's a
way of characterizing something as being
a Turing complete computer or not yes is
there something similar for quantum
computers there a quantum Turing machine
I mean you know kind of criterion you
say this is a complete quantum computer
it can calculate everything that you can
do with quantum computing yes
essentially there is there is such a
thing so you know at the basis at least
my version the way I understand the
Turing machine is that if you have a
Turing complete computer then you can
simulate any other type of Turing
complete computer exactly with a Jessica
Lee normal overhead so essentially what
it says is all computers are equivalent
yeah if there is a problem that is
really hard to solve on one computer it
would not be easy on another computer it
will also be hard yeah so but this is
all based on classical computing when
you only have bit and when you toss them
quantum resource on top of it and the
church-turing thesis doesn't hold
anymore
because we know what they are some
problem that we can solve on a quantum
computer more efficiently than a
classical computer so you sort of
shattered the whole church-turing thesis
okay but there is an equivalent saying
that if you have anything that is
computable on a quantum computer will
also be computable on another quantum
computer so the bottom line is
church-turing thesis does not apply to
quantum computing or let's say quantum
computing breaks the church-turing
thesis but we have also the equivalent
saying that yeah a universal quantum
computer will essentially at the end of
the day be all the same because that's
what we want to look for right something
that is universal something that can do
any possible computation and at the end
of that the according is a
generalization of computing so any
common computer is able to simulate a
classical computer okay a classical
computer can also simulate a quantum
computer but it simulates it with what
we call an exponential overhead so it
means it takes an exponential amount of
operation in the number of qubit to
simulate a quantum computer ok somewhat
the quantum equivalent of the
church-turing thesis says that any
quantum computer will efficiently
simulate any other quantum compared
right and this is again this is a
polynomial efficiently thing going on
for nominal efficiency and on this yes
ok but this now you're taking me a
little bit outside my comfort zone there
I'm a physicist
ok you know I know a little bit on the
computing side but we've talked a lot on
the implementation of quantum computer
but there's a lot a lot a lot of effort
being done by the computer scientists
and the mathematician and the
theoretical physicists to understand how
much advantage does the quantum resource
gave us we know it gives us a 10 -
that's for sure we know that it's more
powerful we know it has a very high
potential but we still don't know really
how much yeah so do we know in which
areas it has advantages I mean you know
getting into the application slowly what
would we do with a quantum computer that
we cannot easily or efficiently do with
a classical computer - other any
examples today or are there any expected
examples I mean what people always say
is once we have one of buting we can
break today's crypto systems yeah that's
probably like we use it a lot as an
example because I mean I'll be honest
this is not the goal of doing research
we don't want to just go around and
crack every year every car out there
that's not a goal but you don't work for
the NSA then I guess we know maybe some
people are there out there till the
vehicle but the factoring algorithm this
is the perfect example that shows how
much of an admission you can give us but
the slight little thing with the with
the factoring algorithm is we're not
sure yeah that it is inherently stronger
and what I mean by that is let's say you
have you multiply two n bit number
gather that gives you about an N square
bit number yeah then if you want to do
the other way around
is extremely hard so it will take an
exponential amount in n to factorize
that number but it hasn't been proven
yet that there exists no classical
algorithm to do it we just don't know
when but it hasn't been proven that
there's non-existing out there okay
the only thing is that we know there
exists a quantum algorithm that can
factor numbers using only a polynomial
amount of operation so this does not
provably show that common computer is
stronger by this is a very strong
contender on showing the power yeah so
how would that work
I mean roughly well this the way it
works is well is the algorithm is called
a shore garden because of Peter shor and
came up with it back then it was working
and I think Bell Labs and now he works
at MIT okay so we discovered or he
developed this algorithm back in 94 and
I will not go to the details of how it
work because it's extremely complex okay
but if we go to to marginal calculus
which is essentially like like the clock
yep you talk module 12 so every time you
hit 12 you start back at 0 and so on
right so he started with the premises
that you can modify the problem of
finding the factor in to finding the
period of a certain number in module
calculus in that period it means like
how many times you need to multiply the
number with itself so that it's equal to
1 in a certain modern module calculus so
he changed a problem to this problem
which are equivalent and he has shown
that you can efficiently find using a
quantum computer the period of the
numbers which you cannot do when using a
classical computer or that please we
don't know how though yeah ok the only
algorithm we know what takes an
exponential amount so you just change
the problem to a different problem that
is related and then show that a quantum
computer can find the answer you're
looking for in a polynomial amount of
time okay so and I don't want to go to
the detail of it because we need a
blackboard and ok good ok and other
examples of what computers are supposed
to be able to do once they kind of work
in the real world
oh yeah there's tons and tons of them
probably one of the first application we
will have
is to simulate quantum system because as
I was saying a little before we can
simulate system on the classical
computer but every time you add an
additional system or an additional
degree of freedom it will always take an
exponential amount more computing power
to deal with it but using a quantum
computer it's kind of intuitive that if
you have a computer that works on
quantum principle that you will be able
to simulate other quantum system yeah it
doesn't sound like a very big surprise
to me I have to say exactly so that's
all that's a whole field of quantum
simulation the potential of this is if
you can really simulate a quantum system
of all the neat ingredient that quantum
system you can start really looking at
how molecule interact with each other or
or example how crystals of certain
material form and all the electrons
interact within it so that's what the
real world kind of connection comes in
yes and then what that can lead at is
exploring new materials one of the very
interesting application is that we could
be able to to simulate how crystal
behave and investigate superconductivity
for example superconductivity is a very
bizarre behavior of certain material
that is somewhat understood using the
bcs theories is well understood but it's
very hard to completely simulate how it
works because it takes so much computing
power to do it so at the end of the day
the only thing we can do is use
approximation and those approximation as
they say well they only approximate they
don't give you the whole thing so now
imagine you can really simulate exactly
the way molecules and the aggregates of
atoms interact with each other and you
can really start understanding this
whole phenomenon of superconductivity
and start engineering or designing
materials yeah that will show
superconductivity at higher temperature
than now because now you can have you
have superconductor that can go maybe at
a hundred nothing it's 100 Kelvin
somewhere around that so it's still very
cool it's not very useful for everyday
application but if you could really
grasp the idea of superconducting using
quantum simulation then you can really
start investigating okay how can we get
a material that would be superconductor
at
temperature right and that would have a
fantastic application either just for
electricity transport so there's no more
electrical loss just imagine building in
a chronic if you have a super if your
electronics are still using
superconductor instead of copper wires
or other resistive elements then there's
no need for cooling down anymore yep
another example is you can start looking
at how the molecules will interact with
each other and that would be fantastic
for designing drugs yeah instead of
designing drugs the way we do now with
you know lots of approximation of
empirical results or not precisely you
can really start looking how it molecule
interact with each other and then design
the drawing the winner should be I was
gonna say that these are all very
special kinds of problems but I guess
that's that's because I'm biased I mean
the kinds of problems we use our
computers today are also special in some
way in that they can be efficiently
implemented with today's computers so is
it fair to say that quantum computers
will not replace traditional computing
but will be mala Gail it's a coprocessor
or you know a 3d card that can do
certain kinds of calculations or
simulations especially well I'm always
hesitant to answer this question because
I don't want to be the guy who gets
quoted in the future saying something a
stupid yeah
just imagine the person who developed
the laser
yeah a few years ago right I mean I was
just a cool little trick II was doing
with lights he he never taught you well
turned out to to play music on a CD
player or doing eye surgery yeah
absolutely but I think one thing that is
safe to say is we know a quantum
computer can do everything a classical
computer can do hmm I mean I don't think
would be far-fetched to think that maybe
I do you know in 50 years 100 years I
don't know maybe every computer would be
a quantum computer but it's just that
the task that the classical computer
would be bad at doing then it's like the
quantum computer would be able to do it
but where is that gonna bring us at the
end of the day I have no idea it's well
we have idea we know where it's gonna go
but there's a whole other possible
possibility that we probably don't even
think of that people would come up with
in the future so
we know for a fact that using quantum
technologies or using a quantum behavior
to build technologies is the next
technological revolution that we're
convince' it just opened a whole
different dimension of what you can do
in terms of tasks in terms of so now
here we talked about computing but
computing is a it's a it's one subset of
things we can do right we can use a
quantum were to do sensing for example I
was saying that quantum world interacts
a lot with the environment and it's very
hard to stay a quantum well then you can
use that at your advantage to do much
more precise measurement or much more
sensitive measurement or sensing this
field of quantum sensing that we're
there is actually a reality right now
okay this has immediate application in
the very near future now you the quantum
computer storage the holy grail of what
we're looking for down the road because
the most general kind of device is the
most general is gonna be the biggest one
is gonna be like once we're back on
computer we can say that we won the
victory over the quantum world and
understand can you control it and
harness it right but in the meantime
there's a lot and lots of discovery that
are being done there's fundamental
discovery just understanding how the
word actually behaved at the quantum
level but there's also small other
little I call them the quantum gizmos
little toys that you build in the goal
of the holy grail but that then in men
time can be used for other tasks example
example yes one of our researcher
actually knew a newest member at the iqc
dr. David quarry he works a lot on
quantum sensor and on immediate
application of what you can do with
quantum information processing and he
developed not so long ago using ideas
developed for quantum information
processing a much more sensitive sensor
for oil exploration who would have
thought that building a quantum computer
will lead to sensors for oil-exporting
exploration right Rhino is also devising
small little detectors to be able to
detect the amount of sugar in the blood
that would be non-invasive so you would
not have to you know to get a sample of
blood to do it we will able just to
sensor and the surface interesting
another thing he did which was quite a
big achievement is he applying idea
that he developed for quantum
information processing - Neutron and
interferometry so he works with the
National Institute for standard
technology in the States and they have
transferometer that is used normally to
image crystals or English material to
very small resolution but the problem
with those is that they're not very
robust they're very sensitive they stop
working very easily and by applying
ideas that we develop in quantum
information processing he's been able to
improve the factor of merit of the
neutron interferometry by a factor of
600 okay people kill to have a an
increase of a factor of two and by
applying what we develop in the name of
quantum computing he's been able to
increase that by a factor of 600 yeah so
those are a example of immediate
application of what we do cool
other applications something we haven't
talked at all yet is quantum
cryptography okay so by doing
cryptography protocol namely key
distribution how to to exchange a secret
key between two party yeah you can use
the quantum state of photons for example
to do that so that if there's somebody
in between trying to steal your
information on this one then you will
detect the person right well the
eavesdropper would be detected and this
is an actual reality right now there are
companies out there that actually have a
commercial product that you can buy
there has been I think it's the 2006
Swiss election the ballots were
transmitted using quantum cryptography
really oh yes it was done in Switzerland
okay so there's a bound out of memory
four or five commercial product out
there that you can buy that that is a
quantum cryptography protocol okay well
it's also useful that you can get you
know concrete benefits from intermediate
steps to the quantum computer and not
just you know like the diffusion guys
yes or you know it's almost 50 years
away and all the intermediate results
are they might be progress towards
fusion but you do anything with these
intermediate results well I'm surely
convinced that the people working in
fusion have some intermediates that it
can be as simple as developing a new
type of detector oh sure I mean in that
way yes some groups around the world
that we're working on superconn
in qubit and then they find out that but
even actually it it happened here also
in Waterloo sometimes the equipment you
can buy off the shelf is just not good
enough it's not fast enough or it's not
precise enough so we just build our own
and then from that you made the
technology advance yeah those are the
side result that always and they are
always welcome but yes as you were
saying a lot of step you know we do
fundamental research we're still at the
point of understanding the quantum world
right and by understanding more and more
you can see more and more of the
possible application you can and then
along the way of working in that very
big project that might may take 20-30
years
we don't know hopefully not as much but
you know but in the meantime there's a
lot of product coming out and then you
will see a lot of technology working
solely on quantum principle showing up
more and more in the very near future I
think such that the kind of time frame
you have in mind 20 30 40 50 years until
we have a quantum computer that is you
know should behave called
a quantum computer it's very hard to say
no I will tell you it's probably not for
for the next five years yeah but you
know at the end of the day you know you
never know what can happen I'll just
take that again the classical computer
as we know it today have the transistor
never been discovered we'll probably
never have a computer just all of a
sudden somebody discovered a transistor
and it was like a massive leap the
development of computer maybe that's
gonna happen also in quantum computing
maybe not like we don't rely on the
onion we do a lot of effort we work very
hard but one thing is for sure is the
state of the understanding and the
controlling of the quantum world
compared to what it was 10 years ago has
made a tremendous amount of progress in
the past and here it's quite impressive
what we can do now with quantum system
one of the last questions I had here was
do we already know how a programming
language or algorithms for quantum
computing would look like would they be
relatively similar in the sense that you
would still have a procedural program
but the single operations are quantum
operations or would they be inherently
different or parallel or is there
anything we can say about that in a way
that I understand it I think it's fair
to say that's what
you know once you have a quantum
processor that works the way you want
then it's fair to say that you know you
might have at some point a high-level
language it comes back to exactly what I
was telling at the very beginning a
language is just a shortcut for
operation being done physically we do
already use some sort of higher level
programming you know you can I'll take
for example this Hadamard gate that I
was talking previously the one that
brings a a zero into a superposition of
zero and one yeah well depending on the
technology
sometimes this Hana more gates requires
three or four different type of radio
wave pulse or microwave bones so you can
either tell your system to say okay do
this post and that post and that post
and that post yeah or you can just
regroup that into one post am Kohanim
are for that then you translate that and
then it just tell your machine to do the
four of them I think it's fair to say
that as we move along and then we start
doing more and more complex operation on
quantum systems there's a higher-level
language we start showing up so what I
was trying to get at was if we look at
systems today there are different
paradigms like event based reaction you
know reactive systems sequential systems
there are different paradigms there are
different ways of describing data are
like zeros and ones or kind of fuzzy
stuff so I was trying to find out
whether we already have a feeling for
what would be a good programming
abstraction or a good you know paradigm
of addressing or working with the
quantum world okay I see your point well
I already mentioned a little bit a
different paradigm that we have right
now there's a circuit base yeah there's
the measurement base and there's the
adiabatic base which one's gonna win the
race I don't know
but each of em are more suitable for a
certain specific system you know the
circuit base is very well suited for
spin base quantum processor because you
know you have one spin is your one qubit
the other spin is your other qubit so
you have no distinct qubit and then you
can make them interact and then make
them into single operation so the
circuit model works very well for those
but if you take a measurement base for
example it's it's fair to say that this
one is very well applicable for photons
because photons one of the very good
thing with photons is they don't
interact
each other so it means that they don't
think oh here is but one of the very bad
thing with photons that they don't
interact with each other so what you can
do the part with the measurement base is
that you start with a very large
entangled state you know in quantum
mechanics interaction with each other
and the entanglement is similar is there
is the same thing when you have two two
quantum system interacting they will
most likely end up entangle
so you can prepare your photon a priori
so at the beginning of your computation
you pretend they're in the certain state
which might be hard but at least you
know you can repeat it as often as you
need but then when you have your state
and you can do your computation by just
measuring it so you bring all the
complexity of your problem at the very
beginning and then once you want to do
your computation you just detect the
photons and that's a something that
we're becoming increasingly good at
detecting is doing detecting for 10 so
where I'm going at is that there is
different paradigm but it's it will be
hard to say which one is winning the
race right now
yeah we're too much of the infancy you
know it's really interesting to be
alright one really has to be careful I
have to be careful to not be spoiled by
the fact that we are so used to
classical computing because when you say
prepare the photon and measure this
sounds all like big machinery to me but
today of course or back then when we
built the first classical computers we
also prepared some electrical charge in
some you know pit somewhere and then you
started the computation so it's it's
quite it's quite analogous it's just
that it's much earlier days we're still
in the earlier days that's why we always
always restrain from trying to reach any
conclusion right I agree because I know
I always mentioned this quote I don't
remember exactly who said it but when
they were talking about the very first
computer the ENIAC yeah and then they
were saying uh he was asked where do you
see the future of computing and he says
well you know I see maybe the need of
five or six computer in the world and
and then nowadays you will we all know
what will happen so I don't want to be
the guy who says something like that
this other guy who said that we never
need more than 640 kilobytes of RAM
exactly there was this famous mr. gates
we know where we're going
but we don't know where we're gonna end
up and every time you have new people
coming in the field there's always new
ideas and it's a field that is growing
extremely fast you know because there's
a very large potential in the quantum
world to do very nice tasks that we're
not able to do nowadays so the bottom
line is we don't know what it's gonna
look like we're not quite sure how we're
gonna do it but we know that there's
something out there and we know the
potential of it and that's why we're
pursuing all the research that we okay I
guess this is this is a nice summary um
I have to say it I'm well we talked for
about an hour or something and obviously
I don't get it completely I did I did
get a better feeling for where we are
and how it's supposed to work but it's a
very abstract topic and tough so I'm
still this is still quite a ways away
from actually like being able to explain
it to somebody else I guess well if you
want to explain it in a very nutshell
here's what quantum information
processing is okay our goal is to
understand harness and control the
quantum world to apply it to specific
tasks that cannot be done or that is
hard to do with today's technology
that's a nice summary yes okay then I
thank you very much Martin for being on
the show here yes thank you very much
that was very interesting
good thank you very much
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio as a radio is an
educational program brought to you by
hillside Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and the
other episodes visit our website at SE -
radio dotnet if you want to support us
you can donate to the SA radio team by
at the website or you can advertise for
se radio for example by clicking on the
dick reddit delicious and slash note
buttons or by talking about us on
Twitter and Facebook you can also
support us by joining team and
shouldering some of the work to contact
the team please send email to team at se
- radio net or if your feedback is
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under a
creative commons 2.5 license please see
the website for details
[Music]